Joe Lett Ward, Jr. papers, Inclusive: 1953-1972, undated; Bulk: 1953-1954, 1963-1972
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Joe Lett Ward, Jr. papers
Inclusive: 1953-1972, undated; Bulk: 1953-1954, 1963-1972
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
4029
Ward, Jr., Joe Lett, 1916 - 2009
10 folders.
This collection contains various materials Joe Lett Ward, Jr. collected as a member of civic organizations in Waco from the 1950s to the 1970s.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Joe Lett Ward, Jr. was born in Waco, Texas, on 1916 November 30. Joe, Jr., the son of Joe Ward and Camille Webb, was a fifth generation Wacoan. He graduated from Waco High School in 1933 and later earned a degree in Mechanical Engineering from the University of Texas in 1937. Following his graduation on 1937 October 25 Joe married his high school sweetheart, Martha Harrison.
Ward worked as a petroleum engineer for seven years but returned to Waco after his father passed away. He assumed control of his father's business, the Joe L. Ward Company, and ran the company until he sold it in 1989. Alongside his business endeavors, Ward was involved in civic organizations throughout the Waco community. He was a co-founder of the Ridgewood Country Club in 1946. Ward and his wife Martha were one of fifteen couples to start the St. Alban’s Episcopal Church. He also served on numerous boards including those of the Waco Industrial Foundation, the Waco Business League, and the Citizens National Bank. After serving four years as a member of the Waco city council, his fellow council members appointed him the Mayor of Waco from 1959 to 1960.
As reflected by the materials in this collection, Ward was also an active participant in the civil rights movement in Waco. The city boasted a relatively peaceful integration of its schools and businesses thanks in large part to a nine-man committee chaired by Ward. Operating alongside the Progressive Community Council headed by Reverend Marvin Griffin, these local leaders subtly introduced integration to the community.
Ward passed away on 2009 October 29 at the age of ninety-two.
Scope and Content
The Joe Lett Ward, Jr. papers provide a snapshot of Ward’s community involvement in Waco, Texas. These materials range in chronology from 1953 to 1972 with some undated materials. The documents are in good condition.
The collection is composed of a single series, I. Civic Organizations. The first three folders contain materials related to Ward’s membership in the Waco Association for Good Government. The organization was concerned primarily with local taxes, school programs, and political involvement. Largely falling within a two year time-frame (1953-1954), these materials consist of the organization’s constitution, clippings, correspondence, and rosters.
The next three folders deal with the Community Relations Committee and its predecessor, a subcommittee operating under the Committee of Fifty. Initially, this nine-man committee worked in cooperation with the Progressive Community Council -- which was comprised of prominent African American leaders -- to integrate Waco’s schools, businesses, and work force. The collection contains correspondence, reports, and minutes from the Community Relations Committee.
The final four folders in the collection stem from Ward’s work with the Human Relations Commission. The commission was formed in 1969 July to handle any human rights infringements in Waco, particularly those dealing with race. It was intended to act as a liaison between the community and the city government. These materials include correspondence, reports, minutes, and procedures.
Arrangement
Prior to the latest round of processing, the materials in this collection were housed in three acidic folders. The documents were organized by the committee that produced them. The original titles have been maintained with one exception. The "Inter-Racial Committee," which was initially a subcommittee of the Committee of Fifty, transitioned into the Waco Community Relations Committee under the auspices of the Chamber of Commerce. These materials are now housed in folders labelled "Community Relations Committee."
The original order of the collection has been maintained, although some of the folders were over-stuffed and had to be broken down further according to material type. The collection is currently arranged in a single series, I. Civic Organizations.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 4029. Acquired 1988-07-11
Related Resources
Related collection materials
Box 65, Folder 12 of the Marvin C. Griffin Papers (#3837) has similar materials from the Progressive Community Council.
Related references
“A True Leader: Remembering Former Mayor Joe L. Ward Jr., Who Changed Life in Waco for the Better.” Waco-Tribune Herald, 2009 November 5. Joe L. Ward, Jr.: Clippings [vertical file]. The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Interview of Joe L. Ward, Jr. by Colbert Held. Waco and McLennan County Project, 2006 June 23. Transcript, Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas.
Joe L. Ward, Jr.: Clippings [vertical file]. The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Joe L. Ward, Jr. obituary. Wilkirson-Hatch-Bailey Funeral Homes. Accessed 2017 August 9.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Ward, Joe Lett, Jr., 1916-2009 -- Archives.
Subjects (Organizations)
Association for Good Government (Waco, Tex.) -- Records and correspondence.; Community Relations Committee (Waco, Tex.) -- Records and correspondence.; Human Relations Commission (Waco, Tex.) -- Records and correspondence.
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- Race Relations.
Subjects
School integration -- Citizen participation.; School integration -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Minutes (Records); Reports.
- Civic Organizations, 1953-1972, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Civic Organizations, the only series in the Joe Lett Ward, Jr. papers, contains materials from three different Waco civic organizations: the Waco Association for Good Government, the Community Relations Committee, and the Human Relations Commission. The materials -- largely correspondence, minutes, and reports -- are products of Ward's membership in these organizations. Overall, the materials are in good condition.
  - Waco Association for Good Government: Address, Constitution, and Clippings, 1953-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Waco Association for Good Government: Correspondence, 1953-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Waco Association for Good Government: Rosters and Telephone Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Community Relations Committee: Clippings and Notes, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Community Relations Committee: Correspondence, Memoranda, and Attachments, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community Relations Committee: Minutes, Reports, and Printed Materials, 1963-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Human Relations Commission: Correspondence, Memoranda, and Attachments, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Human Relations Commission: Minutes, 1969 September-1970 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Human Relations Commission: Minutes, 1970 June-1972 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Human Relations Commission: Procedures, Reports, and Rosters, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)